I mean I wish we would have known each
other years ago because I I really have
I've spent you know over the last 16
years spent an unknown amount of time
doing mental gymnastics on how to get
out of non-competes and uh I bet you I
bet you could have helped me with that a
whole lot sooner yeah yeah I mean my so
you were under non-competes that you
were trying to get out of always yeah of
course interesting y think too small I
got Big Dreams you just start them way
ahead at the end scene started reading
and dodging all the quick like your
Spotify boy I
gots big I got make it for
mys I'm Daniel and I'm Sarah and this is
the inquisitive podcast where usually we
break down why deals fail to close or
struggle to close so that you can learn
valuable lessons and red flags to look
out for but this is a special episode
it's not one of our normal episodes in
the series this is a breaking news
episode Tuesday April 23rd the Federal
Trade Commission banned non-compete
agreements so yeah we're going to break
that down and uh what that means for
deals that are happening right now so it
was a 3-2 vote um so two against it
passed by three good thing they don't
have six people voting in whatever Zoom
room they did that on um and yeah I was
it's technically they haven't banned it
they voted to ban it so that's the most
loyal your thing ever but um it's got to
be published in a Federal Register which
it hasn't been yet as of now and um then
120 days have to pass before it's te
non-competes or technically banned
everyone expects that that will be drawn
out more by legal challenges um the US
Chamber of Commerce already they said
yesterday April 23rd that they planned
on suing April 24th which is the that
we're recording this um so that'll be a
pretty big um you know hurdle uh but
I've been watching this Biden I think
when he was elected it was years ago he
said he was uh challenging or he was
delegating to the FTC to ban
non-competes so I've been telling
clients that every time we negotiate um
you know an employee non-
compete for years and that's so that's
something I thought was really
interesting because I I heard it the
other day from a reel that somebody was
yeah I was on Instagram somebody's like
hey there's like we're in the commentary
period this was proposed a couple months
ago we're going to find out in a couple
days so I got I got word on a little bit
earlier I really don't think that
businesses are going to find I think
business is going to take like years for
it to become common knowledge I had an
interesting timeline because I did I
didn't know there was immin it I mean
I've been following it but it's just
been dragging on for so long and so
yesterday one of my my client said hey
can you retool my employee non compete
um the state they were in is one that
like in the Northeast so um I was like
oh yeah what does that state say about
not competes um I'm gonna have my
associate do a little bit of research
into that so I delegated that to her
thanks Susan look into this uh at 9:00
am and then by the afternoon I was like
stop what you're doing um so this is
inconveniently timed uh I guess none of
this matters really anymore um which is
an unfortunate out of pocket for me um
but like what are the ads the timeline
of that here's like here's the crazy
part for me so like over the last 16
years I've dealt extensively with the
IRS of course I've dealt with a number
of different government bodies but the
Federal Trade Commission is a name that
I've only heard like in passing on like
CNN or MSNBC like I it's not something
I've ever dealt with I thought the FTC
you know kind of like the SEC for me
like I just I know they're there I know
they're you know they they have a lot of
influence on a lot of businesses but
just never in my space um so I was quite
surprised to see that this particular
government body can do this particular
action in terms of of banning something
so like who's the Federal Trade
Commission who's the F FTC like what do
they do and what's your experience with
the FTC I mean not a lot they're the
antitrust consumer protection people so
you know you read about them and like
who's going to control crypto remember
that for a while the like Department of
Agriculture I think was like everyone
was pushing to have them control
cryptocurrency which would have been a
riot um you know like kind of this
jurisdictional question um and I still
wish that that were happening um I think
you might have read about the FDC the
other thing that's going on right now is
um like the
Safeway Kroger merger or something
you know anytime there's some big you
know antitrust issue where there's too
much not enough competition H and too
much kind of
um stuff located under one institution
they're the ones that broke it down and
the Monopoly situation yeah there's
gonna be a really funny joke before we
get too far from the topic and I don't
want to segue too much but there's got
to be a really funny joke to be made
about crypto being under the department
of a like wait did somebody did somebody
at the Federal government here that like
crypto is being farmed and they're just
like oh that's clearly
agriculture yeah they were like well
mining it's Min so I don't know if they
control mining
but
good yeah the FTC so that's interesting
so like yeah I think monopolies and like
you know those like the antitrust that's
like antitrust has been in the news a
lot over the last decade that's usually
when you hear about the FTC and to back
up so from my perspective talk to
clients all the time as a lawyer I get a
lot of people who say um a lot for years
I've had people say well yeah yeah I
signed a nonon beete but those things
are not enforceable so it doesn't matter
and um that has not been true uh
ever somebody said that I used to think
that I used I used to feel that way and
so like I always read my non-competes
I've I've always been under non-competes
like everywhere I've ever worked was I
was under noncompete yeah and I always
resisted signing it and they were just
kind of like yeah well if you want to
work here you're signing it so it's like
a crap I want the job yeah um I never
took it seriously because like I was
always like yeah they're not going to
sue me not one person but then I was at
the very first law uh very first
accounting firm that I ever worked at um
like a big chunk of their executive team
left and opened another competing firm
within a mile away of the office and
like straight up stole process docks and
templates and everything and like like
they they like fired a girl that worked
for the firm and then like helped her
get a job there so she could go in and
like take pictures and like take all
this information yeah and then she came
back and like gave all the information
over they gave it to their attorneys and
like yeah local judge actually shut them
down under the on the grounds of the
non-compete so I was like oh that's like
that's legit like they could do that
yeah I definit so you can do it um I had
an issue like that once um at a um I'm
going to say just like um a
service-based company and with where The
Client List was really important and um
an employee was a competitor so this was
years ago but she was under a great
non-compete um the employee was a uh had
the potential to create her own service
based business and steal the clients
right and so she um we H had her on like
CCTV footage going in on a Saturday to
the office and like taking giant
pictures of say like you know like
client lists and going over to The
copier and opening them and like copying
All The Client List it was like absolute
red-handed and but the process of suing
to enforce it you know it's so um the
law and the judges and the public policy
is so in favor of the employee that uh
in this case it was really brutal
because they H terminated her and then
she filed for unemployment compensation
and so we went to contest unemployment
compensation because it's basically the
employer paying her to you know Live
While She sets up a competitor to go
compete with them and um they hired a
lawyer who does that sort of thing and
and didn't win like they still had to
pay unemployment compensation the whole
time and ultimately that was such a bad
experience I didn't want to devote the
like $100,000 in legal fees to oh wow
and that's usually my advice because I
have more of a business type of advice
so when people do come to me and they
say that I say do you want to spend
$50,000 on pursuing this risking all the
negative publicity because it's you know
real gonna it's not going to look good
on you um when these clients hear that
you're suing some person that they have
an established relationship with and
they will hear she will tell them and
like versus reframe that let's take that
$50,000 how can you you know grow your
business or how can you reach out to
those clients and you know try to
probably better used in other ways yeah
and it's just like emotionally better to
focus on the future and growth versus
you know lost money so so non-competes
like I I understand the purpose and you
know so for like historically
non-competes have been used to keep
people from stealing clients stealing
Trade Secrets uh damaging the business
by leaving and and working in direct
competition it seems like they've always
been
so definitely time bound typically like
two or three years right and then
there's like a geographic element I I
don't think I've ever seen one upheld
that was just like a national
non-compete which now that there's
internet businesses maybe that's
different but no you have to be real
reasonable and toggle like a good
Geographic scope um I think some people
get a little fast and loose and frankly
you know I've been a lawyer since uh 20
um God I've been a lawyer a while and
13 years or something and um whenever I
started that was how we treated them was
okay well maybe it won't ultimately be
enforcable but there's a chilling effect
to get somebody to sign it so we're
going to say you know you can't compete
within 30 miles of any of our office any
of our places of business and you know
it's a restaurant and there's no place
in the US that doesn't wouldn't fit that
you know we're going to get cheeky with
it and that person will not compete
because they're afraid of us and um
turns out judges and the FTC and other
people were Savvy to that and so um they
started really ratcheting it down but I
don't I don't want to you know belabor
it too much FDC can be in charge of this
they can rule National nationally and
that does override um the state laws as
a deal attorney like I I so like I think
that's like so it's how it impacts
employees employers but this is going to
have a major impact on Acquisitions so
in your experience as deal attorney how
have non-competes been used in
Acquisitions to protect the buyer who's
buying a business well like my main
focus is a service based business which
is an accounting practice where The
Client List is its main thing there's a
developed relationship you really cannot
buy those and there would be no market
for them if there was no non-compete but
that's the only real exception that was
provided in this rule was for the sale
of a business and our initial proposed
rule
said you had to be it had to be the
substantial owner of the the business
and they defined that in the initial
rule as a 25% owner or greater like if
you're buying a business the reason why
you would have a non-compete so you'd
have a non-compete for the owner of
course so the person who selling the
business um but then also some like key
employees and stuff would you like you
how would you like that's how you would
keep them in the business right like to
keep them from like seeing Oh the
business sold I'm just going to start my
own like this is a great time to leave
typically you isolate any n um any key
personnel and try to get them under a a
non-compete It's Tricky a little bit and
I always call out third party stuff at
the beginning of an acquisition because
there's no contractual Nexus so you
can't for instance have like I own a
business I'm going to sell it to you and
I I'm G to obligate my employees not to
compete with you that doesn't work they
have to agree to that so there's this
you know contractual nexist the buyer
has to get in front of the key personnel
and get them to sign and non-compete the
seller often won't provide that access
until closing so it it's it's been hard
just functionally to get those folks
under it on and impossible in some
states like California for a long time
um so you know that's where I do my
whole like Southern idiom you know ounce
of preventions worth a pound of cure and
say you know you got a loot down your
Client List um some things in different
Industries like Med Spas where
competition's just Rife because people
built there's no reason you would
automatically know this so let me
explain what I mean and I know you've
had a lot of work
done but what like what happens is
people develop a relationship with like
their aesthetician or their injector
it's very normal to have all the clients
text that person and then meet basically
they're texting that person directly
meeting at The Med Spa so it's an
unbelievably easy way for the person to
leave and take all of their uh clients
with them so in that type of situation I
always some counseling clients they're
going to compete they're going to steal
your clients you need to not let them
you know exchange cell phone numbers you
need to do a round robin where they see
a different person each time so that
they're not building which is kind of
worse for business in a way because his
relationships are good but it's like
preserves the brand a little bit more um
things like that we've been doing for a
long time across businesses and in the
m&a space same thing like figure out who
that sometimes in accounting practices
there'll be like a son of the owner who
has the same name as the seller and it
doesn't own the business so now you know
we're in this position where that person
like you know I don't know the you Smith
Jr can go out and compete and set
literally next door A Smith junior
accounting practice right after there's
a sale and have all of those client
relationships and there's really nothing
you could do about it so like a pretty
big risk exposure that this opens up and
I've like I've been hesitant to take a
position on this because like I
mentioned you know I did the mental
gymnastics get to get out of my
non-competes but at the same time in the
case of an acquisition there's a lot of
use cases for it I it's like just like
General sentiment like I know like you
probably have a different opinion on
this from a legal perspective but like
from a business operations perspective I
don't love contractual obligations as a
tool for retention I would much rather
like retain with performance with
benefit you know in better ways but but
like this is a pretty major risk for you
know a Main Street business buyer so I I
really want to like get into so who it
like applies to and the key employees
and like how it's going to roll out but
um so like at the surface level of the
FTC from what I've read they say that
they're doing this because it's going to
create jobs there it's going to create
more competition people can go from one
place to another to get more wages more
people will start more businesses it's
just going to do a lot for the economy
um from your legal perspective why is
the FTC Banning non-competes why did
Biden you know why did President Biden
run on this you know what what was your
take on it over the last few years why
would they do something like this now I
think it's probably um you know a
good almost free way to spur on some you
know economic uh engagement because all
that stuff is true like there I hear
from a lot of clients and have my entire
career going I want to set up a business
and my first question is under are you
under a non-compete with your existing
employer let's look at it together let's
you know figure that out maybe we need
to negotiate I mean two years ago maybe
year ago I helped a guy
negotiate um out of a non-compete on
exit from a large business where he
essentially paid the business
$100,000 just like they fired him he
paid them $100,000 to get out of the non
compete so that he could go and just
have a different job it wasn't like he
was setting up a business he just needed
to have another job yeah and that's I
mean you see use cases like that and it
does feel super unfair and chilling and
like you know there's so many times that
something can be fair on its face you
know like oh okay um I'm in the middle
of Denver at downtown so if you have
something that says you know you can't
compete within 10 miles like okay well
you're gonna have to move you're gonna
have to move to go find another and that
you're you're have to uppr your whole
family or have no job um you know that's
not good especially with the things that
have happened recently like we had
historically low mortgage interest rates
so a lot of people bought or refinanced
at you know 2.7 to 3% and if you leave a
job and you can't compete now you're
forced to move you know there's a lot of
implications it's huge it can be you
know devastating so I think most of and
I will say I advised clients this way
back when the laws weren't so against or
the you know at the the dawn of the this
era where the conversation had just
started I definitely said yeah it's a
chilling effect it's great get everyone
under a nonap put it in your handbook
because that's the way it was done um
and you would just put it in your
handbook because it's better to have
everyone under a non-compete just in
case and that's uh you know gone away in
the last several years because you can
in Colorado for instance you can get
fined um $5,000 plus attorney's fees for
just presenting an unenforceable
non-compete to an employee
yeah that changed August 1st of 2022 or
2021 I don't remember which one but like
so huge and a couple other states have
adopted that and they they really have
tried to get folks to not just get
everyone under a non-compete and then
you only Su the one person who you
really care about um because all of
those people have to run their lives and
they're looking at their contractual
obligations going to I want to risk my
family's whole future um and uh
almost every employment agreement that
we put out as lawyers or offer of
employment specifically makes a person
say I am not under any agreements that
will be violated by me working for you
so it's like even if the courts weren't
going to enforce it you're you're in a
situation where you have to start off a
new job lying to them or they might not
hire you because you admit you're under
a non-compete even if it's un
enforceable so you're just in this weird
boxed in situation I think there's going
to be a lot more people finding
different jobs I think a lot of people
are probably right now going so can I
leave my job right now or do I have to
wait for the publication in the 120 days
I mean they're probably a lot of folks
who this um opens up a different
opportunities for so it's really
exciting it's just in the context of
mergers and Acquisitions um that's
probably the main use case where it's
gonna it's going to really um C us it's
a 570 page document I I saw I read
through some of it I skimmed it I'm
probably going to upload it to chat GPT
so it can explain it but um uh who does
this apply to is it apply to everybody
is it retroactive like I saw some like
broad strokes and like who it applies to
like on the employment side but like
employees um Executives business owners
like what what have you seen so far I'm
not sure what the final rule is going to
say cuz because it made this distinction
between non-executives and Executives
and then they said they both they were
both treated the same so I'm not
sure I saw there was an income threshold
like if it's like over 150,000 so it
seems like it seems like they're
referencing like the highly compensated
employee rules from like the IR or from
other labor laws like those certain
statutes so I wonder if it'll be a
combination like a senior executive plus
$150,000 Sal or something like that but
I don't know I mean I'm interested to
see and I didn't read the whole 500
thing 500 page thing yet either but
everything I saw they were both treated
the same so the distinction was
immaterial um The Only Exception like I
said was for you know in the sale of a
business but you I think that's like
where we're all going to be like okay so
they have to be an owner of the business
and um you know I wouldn't be surprised
if if the final rule says that in order
to get someone under a non-compete they
have to be an owner I wouldn't be
surprised if there's more people you
know essentially getting ownership like
as a precondition to buying your
business you have to give ownership to
your key employee so that then I can get
them under a NAA be and that would be
interesting right I mean that was
immediately where I went was like oh
gosh so that could be good what's what's
a key employee let's like let's define a
key employee for people because I I
think there's a lot of people who watch
that are new to Acquisitions and maybe
they haven't even gone through a deal
yet so um let's talk about some like key
employees and and what we've seen how
that you know could impact the sale of a
business yeah what do you think a key
employee you've probably been one I
don't know I I hope I've been a key
employee that would be really cool I
mean I
think I don't you're like that's so nice
yeah I you know had a lot of Legacy
knowledge I controlled a lot of the
process docs especially in startups
where like the company's documentation
doesn't always live in a centralized
location sometimes it's spread across
various like founder like uh founding
team employ like founding team members
uh like Google Drives and stuff or like
in their computers so yeah I've always
tried to be like I've always tried to do
things on the up and up like I I I'm
like a business developer like at heart
so I try to keep my relationships so
every time I've ever left a company I've
like transferred everything over I've
done extended um you know extended
transition periods I've offered like
ongoing Consulting so that I could like
you know mitigate a lot of that risk um
but yeah but key key personnel they tend
to control process docs they tend to
have really close personal relationships
with the the customers or clients um
pretty much the first the one of the
startups I was at the first 400 400
clients like I literally closed them
like they the relationship was
originated by me to the point that no
matter what I did like people reached
out when I left it it happened yeah
that's um if so yes uh the way in
mergers and Acquisitions one of my
threshold questions is there anyone who
is an employee who if they left you
don't want to buy the business
anymore and then that's really know like
pretty much so way to SS it out and you
know sometimes the answer is I don't
think so but we'll see um but you know
that's it's been a risk it's been this
way in California um there's been a lot
of times that people say no thanks I'm
gonna not going to sign your non-compete
when you buy the business that I already
work for and people proceed so you know
there is that but I think it's going to
really give people um a lot more
motivation to seriously consider who
could leave and um
completely uh break their business model
so my last question on this was like how
do we handle this like I think this is
like probably how we round out the
conversation is like what do we do
moving forward so I've got so many ideas
so many things I want to talk about but
like staying on this topic does this
change how hard a buyer pushes to have
those conversations with managers or key
employees during due diligence or prior
to closing
you know because like I know sometimes
it happens but it's like typically not
common I mean I think it certainly gives
you a better um explanation and um a
more timely reason to say that a seller
should give you that access I mean this
is one of the few points that I just
give different advice on depending on if
I'm representing a buyer or a seller the
buyer I'm like meet with the employees
as soon as you can the seller should let
you and for the seller I'm like do not
let them meet with your employees until
closing because both are you know the
best approach if you can get a seller to
do it you'll be better off it's no risk
to a buyer I know with your with your
clients you will always index towards
the best thing for them as their
attorney but for the sake of a deal like
what do you think what's your just like
what's your opinion you know your
unbiased opinion as to like when should
this happen should it happen would more
deals close there yeah more deals would
probably close
on terms that were more negative to a
seller if they because you kind of have
people over a barrel um if you're a
seller and you you say hey employees I'm
selling and this is the buyer and we're
really excited um my advice to the buyer
is to always have an written offer
letter for all your employees first time
you meet with them so you know great
that's fantastic well then what happens
if the buyer pulls out the sellers know
you were trying to leave and there's no
there's no buyer now and they feel
really unsettled and they're going to
look for a different job H is just like
well that was fun those were nice people
maybe I'll try to hire them so okay
maybe I'm splitting hairs at this point
but I'm just like I'm trying I'm like
thinking through how we handle this what
if you have a closing like maybe maybe
all closings are like Thursday Friday
now and maybe you have a meeting with a
key employee on like a Tuesday Wednesday
and then they sign an NDA and go on
vacation for a week you know I don't
know I mean that's not to stop them from
picking up the phone and calling and
like violating that NDA but but like is
that like can we get into some kind of
silly you know new ways that we go about
this to mitigate it I think that's fair
I think um you know my advice is usually
broad brush because I do smaller
businesses and you you have to picture
them all talking because they've been
working together for 20 years but you
make a good point they're not all the
you know the front desk person may be
your a key employee they often are but
they might be completely not essential
to the equation and so you you know it
does make sense to not treat all of the
employees equally and to maybe bring
some of those folks into the fold I
think probably more rollover equity and
type of really courting of the employees
themselves will erupt from this in lie
of just you know buying the business
it's going to be a better compensation
plans better incentives yeah and then
that's going to eat in to the sellers
side of things because there's not
enough margin to go around um so the
seller's going to have to take less and
recognize that the you know the key
employees got to have a part of that
deal um and you know maybe that's the
way it should be so well as the as a
broker in this conversation my new
official advice is to budget an extra
$2,500 for all of your Acquisitions to
send your key employees on a cruise
where they have no cell phone service
and have your meeting putting them on
the boat just put like a black bag over
their head put them in a
van that's great advice Dan yeah well I
think we solved it with it well but it
ends it doesn't end in a warehouse
somewhere it ends on a cruise ship like
that's not that bad sure it depends on
how you feel about Cruis so I think I
think I'd take the warehouse 25% or more
employer is like is that or the owner
the seller that owns 25% or more can
still be under non-compete but I think
you mentioned before we started
recording that maybe that 25% is not a
thing is it a thing or is it not a thing
do you know as far as I could tell it
was a thing in the initial proposed rule
the comments were like ah I can't
believe you're going to do that and they
took out the 25% description in the
final rule so it's unclear if there's
going to be a like a different number or
if they're going to come up with some
other way or just leave it open to
interpretation as far as like what a
substantial owner is um but I do think
25% would be corre crazy like there's
lots of key employees that have you know
5% so especially bigger deals geez like
05% so you know that's like um gonna
like the whole Jeff Bezos and Elon mus
they own like you know 10 20% of of
their companies like you couldn't even
get them to be in r on beat so yeah
that's crazy not yeah all right this has
been a special breaking news episode of
acquisitive where we were talking about
the ftc's new ruling on Banning
non-competes what that means for
employees especially uh key employees
and employers and more importantly what
that means for you buying a business in
the Acquisitions process and how do you
protect yourself from the seller
starting another another competing
business or key employees more
importantly even because I think sellers
ultimately when the rule comes out the
seller you'll be able to have them under
a non-compete key employees probably not
so uh have a conversation with your
attorney have a conversation with your
Brokers with your advisers um you know
how can you talk to employees how can
you sus out you know where your risks
are with the uh the Staffing you know
this comes back to our conversations
about due diligence and asking for that
uh employee list even if it's all
redacted just knowing the roles and
responsibilities of each person in the
company because a seller may say there
is no keyman or key person risk um but
you might be able to identify like go
well if this is the only one person that
does all of fulfillment they they have
all the relationships and the seller
says there's no key employee risk well
you know that's not true so do your due
diligence talk to your advisers this
will have massive impacts across the
board on Acquisitions on employment in
general I think ultimately ends up being
good but we do need to learn some new
processes there's a concept I didn't get
to talk to Sarah about I think that
we're going to start to see some
development on the NDA side
non-disclosure agreements are still
allowed so you can still have key
employees and managers sellers
non-disclosure agreements to not talk
about certain parts of the deal so I'll
explore with Sarah uh how far that can
go and and maybe that's part of the
solution so this has been that special
uh breaking news episode of acquisitive
the acquisitive podcast thanks so much
for listening if you got any value from
this please uh like And subscribe drop a
comment below if you have any questions
about Acquisitions that you'd like for
us to answer and we'll get back to
talking about why deals fail to close
next week see next
[Music]
time bigger than anybody ever